[Music]
so tin this is going to be an interview
that we're gonna put out as part of a
little series called Jordan Peterson and
the left or what can the left learn from
Jordan Pederson that we got in contact
first because you wrote the first I
think the first spectator profile of
Jordan Pederson at about the same time
as I brought out my documentary and
you've described yourself as an old
lefty so I think it's really interesting
to kind of to pull that apart kind of
where what is have the reactions been to
what you've put out there what have you
gone on a journey with all of that staff
and and what do you find kind of really
enticing about Jordan Peterson
so I from a working-class background in
London I was a journalist when I started
off then I started writing books I've
also worked in the meantime as a
journalist for The Guardian primarily
I've been a columnist on the Guardian
till the end of last year but I've
always seen the Guardian as my natural
home I've read the Guardian for as long
as I can remember so that I'm certainly
a leftist to that extent and we've
pretty much probably discovered Jordan
Peterson and more or less the same time
maybe all of you I think well I don't
know I was I was I was I will I don't
even remember how I came across Jordan
Peterson other than in the context
because one thing I haven't said about
my career is I now as well as write
books teach writing and I've been
studying how stories are generated and
the shapes of stories and the structure
of stories and that's how I came across
Jordan Peterson way before we got into
this whole debate which has somehow got
all in tang with politics which I've
never seen Peterson primarily as a
political figure I mean I know people
interpreting that way and in some ways
he is a political figure but that's kind
of not what interests me about him what
interests me about Peterson is is a
purely professional interest in some
ways is he's understanding of where
store
is come from and why we need them and
how they are laid out in our
imaginations both psychologically and in
terms of the culture in other words in
films in theatres in whatever the novels
I mean you know if what if my practical
question was if I can crack the problem
of what makes for a compelling story
it's going to make me a better novelist
you know and I'll be able to use that
tool and teach that tool and Jordan
gives some brilliant lectures on stories
whether they're the Lion King or whether
they're Hamlet or whether they are the
Bible but well I'll get to the Bible but
then the smaller stories like Pinocchio
you know these modern fables he started
you know that was his starting point as
it were and I followed all those stories
his analysis of these stories buting the
beasts being another one Pocahontas you
know he was I mean he's from his
analysis and Pinocchio is particularly
brilliant you know and I I've um I've
tried to you know I've read Joseph
Campbell the mythologist Ariat from you
know who wrote the uses of Enchantment
about children's stories I've always
been gripped by the idea that there's a
kind of underlying story bubbling up in
a soul that will as artists trying to
somehow inflect in our own way but it's
always in some senses the same story and
if it is the same story what does that
story mean what is that story why does
that make us moved or interested or
involved and that's where I think Jordan
Peterson is absolutely fascinating he's
fascinating about how the individual
what he's a psychologist and it's the
how how this thing works with respect to
psychology and the most important thing
from me quite apart from his work with
you know these stories modern myths was
as you say his investigation into the
Bible
and I've always been fascinated although
I'm an atheist I'm always been
fascinated by the power of the biblical
stories I often found myself looking at
these huge cathedrals and churches that
sprouted up all over Europe you know and
and ask myself well what's that about
you know why was this story so powerful
I mean yeah it's the defense against
death if you want to be cynical but hey
you know it could be lots of other
stories you know why is this one so
unbelievably powerful and what does it
mean for it to be so powerful and pieces
I think brilliantly answers that
question in the biblical lectures he's
done and he really changed me those
lectures who genuinely did I think
changed the way I lived my life because
he came to this very very important
conclusion which I'm pretty convinced by
I don't think I'm ever 100% convinced
about anything but I'm very convinced by
his idea as I I'm someone who's suffered
depression and depression is like a
crisis of meaning in your you know it's
the worst thing about depression is not
about being miserable it's being having
a life that seems utterly meaningless
and that's why it's such torment and
Petersons in a way tries to answer the
question how do we as an individual
that's a bit of a paradox how do i as an
individual acquire meaning because
meaning is the most important thing any
of us could have you know there's
meaning as it you know if you don't know
and yet no one could quite say what
meaning is which I think is interesting
in itself no-one says well I want a
sense of meaning what is a sense of me
what is meaning and Petersons I think it
knowledge is that mystery but also it
says well you know if you want a sense
of meaning it's not about just doing
what you want it's not about just
following your bliss as Joseph camp
would be or having a much fun as
possible or or even necessarily being
happy no absolutely no not necessarily
being happy it's there were more
important things than being happy and
and I've also fair
that to be true in my life I'm 62 now
and I've been through a lot you know and
I found that many things that
unhappiness has given me so much you
know unhappiness has given me so much in
terms of in terms of meaning trying to
pick through the bones our once our
unhappiness is what one enriches you and
that's the story that is the story of
nearly all great stories that that
suffering is a way of raising yourself
above your animal condition if you
choose to let it be and that the
suffering that involves in a change in
yourself and this is what we teach in
story narrative which all great stories
are about a change of one condition into
another condition and that's what makes
a story compelling it's this making this
change and the the the the pursuit of
this goal of change is what actually
what we mean when we talk about meaning
that somehow to aim for something higher
than yourself even if you can't quite
name it I mean I would use you know that
aim the word for that same as
authenticity maybe that's one of the
words I'm not used to try and discover
my own goal is to be an authentic person
to be a real person because I had a very
strong sense when I was younger that I
wasn't very real that I was kind of
two-dimensional that I was a bit like a
cardboard cutout and I could be blown
away by the wind at any moment and my
experience of life and going through a
fair bit of suffering I would say as
everybody does I think I've probably had
you know that's probably who some worse
experiences and some better experiences
in other that this that this suffering
has forced me to engage with what it
means to be alive and has enriched me in
some sense
and that struck a very loud chord when I
you know not dying anyway glamorize so I
don't think anyone should seek out
suffering you know but but I was very
taken by Peters's message that life is
it's not about being happy life is about
suffering okay well that sounds a bit
that's a bit a aurash in this day and
age when a lot of people have a very
pleasant life you know and they don't
really suffer that much and I get that
you know you can have a very nice life
it it's just not very deep life you know
it's just not a very profound or
resonant life and somehow in my
experience when I meet people who've
been through really lousy crap somehow
they're kind of interesting you know
they're more interesting than richer
they're deeper but they may be amiss
others might just be you know it might
have done the wrong thing with that
stuff and become just boring assholes
you know but I mean but it gives you an
a strange opportunity because when
you're you know in a in a crisis you
have to question your life very deeply
and you have to say what's gone wrong
now as Peterson would point out a very
common response to that is someone else
did that to me society did that to me
the ruling class did that to me men did
that to me women did that to me white
people did that to me you know and
there's something in there but it's not
really a sufficient on my case you know
as a working class boy not very
working-class anymore you know the the
ruling class the wealthy people the
upper-class did that to me you know
deprived me of a decent education
deprived me of any material pleasures
when I was up until I made my own money
you know and but it's not you know and i
but i but i really have a gut resistance
perhaps again from my background as a
kind of sort of respectable
working-class self-help kind of ethic
that it doesn't do you any good
even if it's true to cast yourself in
that role your story is not going to be
very good one there's not gonna be a
very nourishing one if you put yourself
in that row might be easy it might be in
short term you know it's rather like
junk food a junk thought it's like oh
it's all their fault it's a little bit
therefore but as Peter says it's also a
little bit your fault and maybe it's a
lot your fault
you know and and you've got to watch
that thought because if your or
depressive like I am you know how that
can flip over into a kind of acute
pathological guilt about sort of you
know I'm the worst person in the world
because everything's my fault and I
think that's a danger I've spoken to
Jordan about this about this idea that
you know this I this I this idea of
intense personal responsibility which he
advocates I'm not so much with him on
that you know I think you could you can
get a bit carried away but I do think
the modern left has lost lost touch with
their essential liberal trope that we as
human beings at our deepest level are
individual souls that are all value you
know and we have an intrinsic instinct
as it were for morality and that
morality is important and that's the
modern project let's not think about it
you know and let's get on with our lives
let's buy our iPhones let's stay on the
online let's watch love Ireland but
let's not think about it because
actually it's not really a soluble
problem and you know it's all about
power anyway blardy blar well you know
maybe it is a soluble problem and I
think Jordan Peterson is the first
person in some way it's not the first
person there are the people Alan Watts
is one of them and Joseph Campbell's
another thief he's really you know and
you people who've really approached that
question but I'm not a great one for
distracting myself and the big problems
of life because I wouldn't be a very
good novelist if I was but with that
territory goes a lot of uncertainty and
fear and and I'm just a to go together
and
and and yet also fascination and meaning
and I I guess I have a similar take and
why after I interviewed Jordan in
October last year I then kind of thought
I want to turn this into a documentary
precisely because I had a real sense of
how important and how meaningful his
message was and I had already got this
this real impression that it was being
lost on a lot of people because they
couldn't get past the political stuff
absolute and absolute and so that's why
I made I made it into the documentary
that I did was to sort of to try and
create because it's so impenetrable I
mean where do you start with Jordan
Peterson there's these lecture series
there's so many different ways in or
there's so many difficult ways in
because you've got to watch so much of
it to understand and so I tried to make
this documentary to kind of I guess I
already had in the back of my mind a lot
of my progressive friends and their kind
of reactivity to what he was saying and
to try and say no no look at what he's
actually saying look at the kind of
Jungian underpinnings look at the story
look at the the deeper message of what
he's what he's doing and I guess it's
it's been a constant kind of I found
myself in that conversation so often oh
and I mean we both we both feel like the
political lens is probably not the right
one to look at Jordan Peterson through
but it's almost impossible in this
highly politicized world not to kind of
look at him through that lens or at
least for him to be pulled into that
frame all the time so I'm interested as
a fellow but we both probably consider
ourselves at least or coming from the
left yes so I'd love to hear have you
have you had arguments with people many
and many arguments up that I've kind of
given up you know because I mean it's
really being quite depressing in a way I
mean I thought we know when I when one
tries to and this is really one of the
things that pizzas and rails against and
I think very rightly is that when one
tries to engage with people on certain
subjects they're not really
they're very resistant to discussion
though rather just start shouting at you
or accusing you that the of being you
know a fascist or something or a sexist
or something you know oh they'll throw
person abuse at you and and and instead
of saying yeah okay all right well you
might not find this a very attractive
but what's your answer what's your
rationale you know I mean if Jordan
Peterson has a meta-study
showing that men and women are
fundamentally different in the way they
behave in all cultures and there are
like hundreds of studies that all show
the same thing what do you say to that
you know I mean I don't think it's
politically sexist well that's what they
say to that but it's like why is that
sexist I mean you know you don't you
know it's it's it isn't sexist that's
all to me to say that men and women
might and you know you only have to say
might to get into big trouble might have
different in warm proclivities and this
is the reason it's so taboo is because
the social constructionist view has so
gripped the left and I thought it had
died you know at the end of the coming
down the Berlin Wall and the failures of
Maoism the failures of the failures of
communism January which is a hot which
is embedded in a whole mindset Marxism
and later post Marxism I didn't say that
when I was at university I studied
political science so like Jordan I
studied to territorialism and I studied
the Russians and I studied how the
mindset worked and it was terrifying
like him I just thought this is
terrifying but I thought you had gone
you know I thought that was dead but
what I've seen is it being its recruit
recrudescence through the Academy
through the universities suddenly it's
back the difference is they don't know
it's Marxism or they call it
post-modernism you know but in fact it's
the idea
that only power matters that there's no
absolute truths they're all truths of
relative this to me is garbage you know
I mean it's I mean you can you can make
an intellectual argument about it but
it's still very patently not true you
know that some values don't tell me that
dignity isn't a real thing don't tell me
that respect isn't real it'll thing
don't tell me that love isn't a real
thing you know that it's all power it's
not true you know I know it because I
know my inner self and my final point of
reference is my inner self my soul if
you want to use religious terminology
though I'm not religious but my soul is
where I look for my final authority not
to the group that I belong to or not to
the group but anybody else belongs to
I'm not interested in I mean I'm vaguely
interested I recognize it has a part to
play but finally and fundamentally it's
the individual that matters and how
could I think anything otherwise as a
writer if any job is about the
individual voice it's the job of the
novelist you know if you know films are
collective projects writing a novel is
the ultimate individual acts the
ultimate individual voice and even that
is coming under pressure now you know
people they have they have I think
they're called something like they're
not called morality readers but their
policy reader diversity readers know how
editors now who check you know that you
don't have a uni appropriate you don't
have any inappropriate opinions in your
you know even for your characters that's
a really deep sickness as far as I'm
concerned that is that is totalitarian
thought and it's totalitarian thought
not in the government but it's the
totalitarian thought mindset but I see
on the Mars
it hasn't expressed itself in government
yet we're still too basically a plural
society but that mindset this I know
what's Rhys and you if you don't agree
with me or wrong and what I love about
pizza is that he says you don't know
anything you know you're very small the
world is very big and you can't possibly
grasp it so have some bloody humility
you know and I think that's so true
because the world is incredibly complex
and we all have to construct stories
around it but very few of us seem to
have the courage to say I don't know
what the hell is going on and I'm just
little me so let's listen to each other
and try and work out what the hell is
going on but people are so scared of the
chaos that that involves the sheer
magnitude of the problem if you like but
they retreat into these little rigid
narratives and say well that's the way
things are you know and I hate that I
mean I really viscerally hate that the
idea that people insist out of fear of
the complexity of the world
I'm just understandable but you know it
leads to hell at least a schvitz
and it leads to the gulags you know once
you are too scared of reality and
reality after all especially with the
rise of the Internet has revealed itself
to be so complex that the more complex
it is the more terrified would become
and will out control the world seems to
be the more we retreat to our bunkers of
certainty and yet you know if you're
being human means anything in a kind of
mentally eeveelution Airy sense its
tolerance of uncertainty is to be able
to say I don't know let's work it out
and if you can't do that what have we
got
we've got totalitarianism so I'm very
much Ben Jordan Peterson on that all the
stuff about women I mean I think all
that's and and and and and the pose I
mean he's right about the postmodernist
I think he's right about Marxists I
think he's quite right so whether there
is quite as powerful as he thinks there
I don't know but you know I think he's
he's identified a really a really clear
and present danger and he's had the
courage
to stand upright because I was talking
to you before we were running is that
the trouble with the postmodern
neo-marxist line is that it invariably
puts you on the defensive the moment
they come at you with these ideas you're
racist you're a sexist you're a
misogynist you're LBGT averse whatever
you know you always lamb offer you know
the whole dialogue is about putting you
on the back foot and making you feel oh
I am a bad person I should shut I know
all right maybe you can go and go or I'm
not gonna engage with you know you think
I'm a bad person but the point is you
start to shut down you start to be
scared you know to express your view and
I think that's yeah and you also drew
some really interesting parallels with
the show trials in communism and this
sort of sense of we've all got this
internalized sense of well there's
something where I've done something
wrong at some point that all of these
even Spanish Inquisition and like though
I think that's that's the sort of truth
that pretty much every great Inquisitor
has come to it's like everyone has an
internalized sense of shame around
something if you can find if you can tap
into that everybody wants to confess you
know and their their sin because they
feel they've done something wrong I
don't know if it comes out childhood or
some ancestral inheritance but everybody
deep in their heart feels they've done
something refresh an idea of original
sin yes it is it's it's it's certainly
akin to that you know and that need and
one of the most loathsome and pathetic
spectacles I I see is is is people
desperately so I'm sorry I'm sorry I
said that you know I'll never say it
together because that just makes it even
worse the moment you did better but you
know it's a groveling that goes on for
people speaking what they see is their
truth but that is it is really under
threat I think and and it's not and it's
self-censorship and it's it's by cutting
and you know the BBC also i've always
been a huge admirer and supporter of I
think there's something in the idea that
their agenda has become narrow and
narrow and narrow and you know they're
thinking within very small boxes now and
I'm very reluctant to align myself
would say the Daily Mail which I loathe
detest and despise and let me make that
absolutely clear but the idea there's a
kind of bias within the window in the
DBC I think it's hard to argue against
it you know I think they are quite
within that sort of cultural framework
you know you kind of know what they're
gonna say before they say it there's not
a real there's nothing real which is why
the intellectual dark web is developing
so powerfully is because the national
broadcaster is not giving us those
genuine honest inquisitorial
conversations that they used to you know
all they're all we're really getting is
this is what the BBC although they will
never put it that way this is what our
collective view is on morality it's goes
back to the wreath you know idea that we
have to educate the public because they
kind of fear the mob you know and that's
that's something I again coming from
worthless background I don't see the mob
to be feared you know I all the
working-class people on you although
they didn't have very appropriate
opinions a very decent good people you
know and I'm much better than their
so-called betters you know morally so I
don't have that fear that mob I trust
people to be good people but there's
still that sort of elitist idea that you
know if we don't sort of educate these
these plebs out of their house out of
there you know nativism you know they're
all going to begin marching up and down
giving Nazi salutes and you know on
beating up their wives and that's just
nonsense
there's a yeah there's so many things
there to pick up on really interesting
because one of the things that you often
hear is people on the Left saying oh
well he talks about cultural Marxism
there's no such thing and what you're
expressing is yeah there's cultural
Marxism there there's cultural Marxism
ii-in in literature already because
people are and I think I feel this as
well like it's almost it's almost more
it's far more than politics like the
most chilling effect is being had at the
level of the dialogue of what's allowed
to be said you know it's not allowed to
be said yeah and that I think is is
where we both should have share myself
as a journalist you you as a novelist
both
share a lot of concerns around what it
means if you've got a public space where
certain things are not allowed to be so
I feel incredibly passionate about that
you know I mean I just think again as a
novelist I've got to be I've got to be
allowed to be wrong you know without
even bit without being accused of being
you know 27 different things that are
all to some extent or other evil or you
know to be disapproved of the point is
I've you know I've got to have my
characters be able to express the way
real people are you know I can't just
say this is the way they should be
because that's the death of literature
you know and that's why literature and
arts in Russia died the moment the
Communists took over from a wonderful
rich history of literature and art
suddenly dead you know
and same with maoism you know I mean I
don't know about the history of Chinese
culture I've got no idea it's very
different culture and now they seem to
be emerging out of it in some ways you
know but you know I think it's it's
terrifying for an artist what is
happening and what's particularly
terrifying about it
he's quite a lot of artists to signing
up to it you know they're signing up for
the sort of you know I was most shocked
of all I don't know there are some
shocking things that happened in the in
the lot in my lifetime I'm certainly on
the subject of the 7/7 bombings in
London I was shot and Salman Rushdie how
many of my so-called left colleagues as
it were apologists for what was
happening simply because they were out
in America and therefore anything that
sort of you know anything that and also
cultural Marxism supposes that all
cultures are equal which i think is
rubbish I just don't think all cultures
reap I think some cultures like cultures
like people some are better than others
some are nice that some are cruel and
others some are more noble than others
some are more you know they're like
they're just like people as Plato
observed you know and I think the idea
that everything has a kind of equal
value I was gonna say the most
disgraceful moment of artists betraying
their trade to me was
the Charlie Hebdo massacres took place
and the American pen you know after the
award was given to Charlie Hebdo for the
extraordinary bravery I mean my god yeah
I knew they were in the front line of
Islamic state at that time they knew it
you know and they weren't on publishing
not just you know because they took the
the Makia Islam as they did with
everything else you know that's what
they did they were sort of riding on
France you know and that that though
American writers stood there and refused
to turn up for that ceremony because
they disapproved a Charlie Hebdo that
made me want to be sick I mean I was so
disgusted by those I mean these are
writers
these are writers that people should be
write up a heart of free expression you
know and and that they are selling that
out I think is shocking beyond belief
there's you know there's two things here
one I've talked about especially because
you can look at it you can look at this
sort of wave of cultural Marxism and
sort of what people can say what they
can't say and all of this sort of media
latin media creation as okay we we don't
like it but you can also look at it as
it's backfiring tremendously look at
Trump look at brexit for me those are do
things absolutely well would direct
responses to what I've kind of called
the shadow of liberalism this sort of
this feeling of inclusivity that
includes only people that sign up to
this this this this this and this and
anyone who doesn't think like that is a
bigot is a yes and I think especially in
America this is what created this is
what's created the political backlash
that we're seeing in the UK in the US
and this is I cannot understand how
progressives or suppose the progressives
cannot see this that some of them are
now sort of doubling down and like oh
wow it's far worse than we thought that
they must be these people must be even
more evil than we thought they were yes
yet before the the American election he
had Milo you know Palouse who was an
openly gay man who talks about his black
boyfriend's getting mobbed a like these
are not personally
or these are not personally bigoted
people this is this is something that
that didn't fit with the kind of narrow
that's it the net people I mean I don't
know much about Marlowe but I think
that's one example but I mean I do think
it's interesting that I think a lot of a
loss of a loss of manifestations are
appearing of political philosophies both
in political parties and sort of on the
ground as it were that just don't fit
anybody's particular narrative the terms
right and left do not really apply very
well anymore
I can finally quite find it hard to put
myself in that spectrum anymore I don't
really know what it means anymore you
know and it's why I think there's this
terrible panic to get Jordan Peterson in
the right wing you know because you know
he's not right wing you know he's not
any wing he's a thinker that has a lot
of his own ideas and you know I mean
though the Kathy Newman interview being
a hilarious
version of you know that's the most
transparent version I think of what
we're talking about people trying to be
forced into a box you know by the
dominant so what you're saying
narrative so what I'm saying no I'm not
saying that but you know it's very
insidious it's very dangerous I think I
I think something's changing I don't
know what and I don't know how fast and
I don't know what's gonna happen you
know but I do think Jordan Peterson is
someone who's had a lot of guts to stand
up for against if you like people who
did not want to have this conversation
you know and he's just saying let's have
the conversation and he's got his point
of view fair enough I'll give him don't
call him you know don't try and flush
him down the toilet because he's a devil
you know it's it's ludicrous absolutely
ludicrous so I don't know I don't know I
don't know where we were this is all
gonna take a stated I mean you know I'm
I'm not particularly optimistic but as
you say things are changing then there
are there are shifts happening under the
surface yeah where they're leading I
don't know they could be leading to
populism they could be leading to yes
they could be leading to a kind of mob
rule certainly that's what happened with
mid brexit to a certain extent they
could be in empowering the elites they
could be leading to the breaking up of
the posts modernist neo-marxist
standpoint or they could be increasing
that I don't really know no one seems to
know it's just like it was a very
interesting Adam Curtis short film the
other day it suggested that the powers
that be if they exist these powers that
be as opposed to just being a chaotic
slithering of different interest groups
the powers that be are almost willfully
turning the narratives into snake pits
of chaos because it just makes you go oh
well because you don't know what else to
do they go oh well I don't know you know
and I've many times been hit by that
says this is I can't deal this anymore
I don't know what the hell's happening
you know I just can't make sense of this
anymore and I think you know one can say
okay that's just that's just a phase
that we're going through and we'll come
out of it or you could say actually
there are there's intelligences behind
it that are actually conspiring to make
the world a more confusing contradictory
and therefore manipulable place and I
don't I don't know I mean I'm confused
you know at least I'm not afraid to
admit now I'm confused which helps might
be maybe I get I guess for me the way
that I can frame it is to just pull this
apart it's like you can have and I
wonder if I'd like to hear sort of maybe
Jordan Pederson framing in this way as
well cuz I do think like one of my
criticisms of him would be that he
certainly comes across as speaking in a
very combative way when he talks about
the left yeah that I think is not going
to help convert
people like I think I think it he's
almost been like roped into one side of
the culture wall and I think partly
partly that's that he just keeps being
dragged down to the political level by
by people who are interviewing him but
what I'd love to hear him say is
something like okay these values that
you hold so dear quality don't if you
could bring himself to say diversity but
certainly fairness fairness as a value
these are good values but if you make
them your primary axioms then you're in
trouble you're basically every lesson
from history shows that if you make
fairness your primary determinant to the
political system you just end up in
chaos or you end up in you end up in in
hell almost immediately well well that's
one of the issues I have with Jordan
Peterson is that I think it's true that
if you make fairness at outcome if you
like the political aim then you are in
trouble but I do believe in fairness and
I do believe that that the system as it
were is run in favor of the rich and
powerful and I do believe that the
system has to be to some extent
moderated by the state you know and I
grew up at a time when I was saved by
the National Health Service I was a very
sickly baby I was able to go to
university I received a grant for it at
the age of 27
you know I VIII went to a grammar school
you know good school from a
working-class area might the benefits of
the state intervening to promote
fairness is not something I'm against
but I can't get down with equality of
outcome I can certainly get down with
equality of opportunity and I think
Peterson is the same but I think he's he
spent too much time I think trying to be
sort of an apartheid low bourgeoisie you
know person who's just gonna go I don't
care
he don't like guys say you know he's got
a bit he's got a bit drunk on that I
think you know and he might want to
enter it's not for me to say what he no
he should do but it would be wise I
think
if he could you know perhaps as you say
talked about and he has talked about he
has talked about fairness he does talked
about the proper role of the left-wing
he has talked about the fact that you
know there is a place for that but it's
just very hidden you know and I think he
might want to he might want to you know
rather than be led all the time by what
other people trying to lead him into
this into this snake pit of not very
healthy narratives so no let's look at
this side you know I am I'm you know and
this is why I this is where I doubt
sometimes doubt how much he has invested
in the idea of you know shall we say I
mean you said he supports quality
opportunity for instance you know
okay well I'm completely down with that
bit you'd only hear that from him very
much
you know he should shout it from the
rooftops you know he should if he's got
liberal and leftist credentials if you
want to call it that way he should be
shouting from the rooftops and you know
he doesn't very much you know I think
he's you know he's quite an T status as
well as being an T but he was supports a
you know he sports a public health
system he was sports the National Health
Forum says we're so having Canada I mean
it's not what you know it's not what the
neoliberals want to do it's not what the
Conservatives want to do you want to
strip back the state to nothing so he's
a much more nuanced thinker politically
and he allows himself to be presented
that's because he's got he's got very
very overexcited perhaps by the idea
smashing down the canals of the I think
for me it's this kind of realization
that what started as really valuable
contributions on the left like
marginalized voices being heard a view
of the people who are being left out of
society all that sort of stuff and in
which is essential has turned into
something of a religion and I think a
lot of people are starting to realize
that it is actually being seen as a
and that blasphemy against it in any way
or being seen as a blasphemer against it
only way is is incredibly toxic or is
incredibly it's it's a career-ending
accusation to be thrown at someone which
is now starting to put certain topics
off off off limit now it's very toxic
very toxic indeed yes the human mind is
a religious mind we think religiously we
don't think rationally you know we think
whether in our religion is Christ or
social or post Marxism post
post-modernism and they're Muslim
they're all religions you know the
liberal view is is is is that to go back
to an earlier point is that we don't
know you know and that's the anti
religious point that's saying I don't
know let's work it out that's where
that's what everything comes down to can
we say to each other I don't know let's
work it out you know not saying and the
religious view is now I already know you
know I think that's what I think
Peterson puts his finger on with a
totalitarian view you know is that that
it's he made the religious point that
the devil is somebody who said they
didn't need or an entity that said they
didn't need any knowledge outside of
what they knew no that was the beginning
end of reality is what they knew there
was nothing beyond that and that in a
strange way is kind of where we're at
you know with neo-marxist and post
notices like you know the beaming you
know an ending of the world is what I
know and that I know it I look I'll look
like I think I don't know anything you
know and that's humility I know any it's
very prideful to say you're humble I'm
not saying I am but I do think humility
is a virtue that should be very much
treasured and aimed for you know and the
idea and the beginnings of humility is
to say it's a very very tough world to
understand people are very complex the
world is very
complex and before you start organizing
his have a think about that because you
can end up in hell very quickly you know
and and and you might have been born
into a generation that didn't know how
but it's happened time and time and time
again through our history that could
happen very quickly now because of the
internet here interconnectedness and I
don't think I do think Peters is right
about the Academy I the academic
assumption is failing in its duty you
know I don't think it's teaching people
to think in the way that they once said
it's also become part of this this
malevolent kind of limitation of
thoughts you know and when they when
that's happening in the universities
which Peters have talked a lot about you
know you are training the next
generation of leaders and that's a
dangerous path to go down and that's the
totalitarian nine set you know to me
you've got to have humility about what
you know and yet you've also got to have
conviction about what you believe so I
have convictions about values and one of
those values is freedom individual
freedom of thought now I can't I can't
defend that to you in a logical way
except by introspection and thinking
what's more precious to me and be able
to think what I want to think I mean
though the evil of the communist
societies was you weren't even able to
think and that's kind of the way we're
going is that oh I can't have that
thought because it's a misogynist
thought or a racist thought so I won't
have that thought you know although it
might be an interesting thought you know
and it might not be at all misogynist
they might leave me at all racist but
you're scared to have that thought
because that little kernel of guilt
inside you is activated you know and I I
think that's that's a very dangerous
place given how collective we are as a
species how we love to join in with the
mob how he loved to believe we're
individuals by acting in a very
uninhibited istic way how we love to
have the approval of all the people
around us how he loved to fit in how he
hate to stay
and out how we you know and all these
this a very really what we call its
group nature tribal nature you know is I
only under the surface very and it's
getting closer and closer to the surface
that tribalism which is which is the
opposite really of enlightenment values
and says no we're not just a bunch of
tribes with precious individuals yeah
this is this is something I fear because
I my sense is that some lessons have to
be learned the hard way and I have a
sense that it's the a big thing that
that we have lost is the lived
experience of those who learnt those
lessons the hard way
the second world war generation and
that's what I fear is that it's now a
whole lifetime since the since the
lessons will learn the hard way in the
Second World War and what we're seeing
is as we lose that sort of sense of
those lessons being learned and all of
the structures that were built up after
the Second World War that we may have to
learn those lessons again the hard way
one could also ask that question about
the fall of the Berlin Wall you know
which is much more recent you know and
and that's that's my masses as bad as
you but that was 40 years later than
that than the end of the Second World
War there's plenty of people who
survived that you know who who can give
their testimony to where that way of
thinking dies and you and I have to pick
up a bias alternates and to know how
those people but you know is he on the
list
after all he's no white man does anyone
bother reading him anymore
why listen salts man soon when he's a
white man with a beard you know because
he's got why does since dusty ask you
know he's a dead old dead white man no
this is you know you listen to
voices that have something interesting
to say and once you start saying we
don't listen to you because you belong
to the wrong ethnic gender group we'd
only hear what you got to say because
it's only about power all you've got to
say is tainted by a desire and which is
just you know that's a sick way of
thinking about the world
it's just not true it's just not sure
yeah and I want to pick up the point you
made before like humility kill him that
so really that's the really key point
and in my interview with with Peterson I
asked him what are the prerequisites for
genuine knowledge and he said fear of
God is the beginning of wisdom
and he said psychologically that means
that what you don't know is more
important than what you know that God in
this sense is standing in for the
mystery or the sum total of the world
that you don't know I think unique you
need to think you need to hold that as
if your life depended on it I think
that's a very important point and it's
something Peterson hasn't talked nearly
enough about which is what he means by
God you know when people think oh he's
sort of Christian well what does he mean
by God he doesn't make this point but
I've read enough of his stuff and looked
it's not lectures to know exactly what
he means by God what he means by God is
all the stuff you don't know and don't
understand and the future which you
don't know and understand well that's
one meaning of God I guess there's two
meanings actually you know but but but
that he doesn't see it as some sort of
supernatural entity that's going to
guide your outcomes if you believe in
him to some happy ending you know he
says that's the fundamental human
orientation towards what they called God
at the time of writing Bible was that
thing that they didn't they couldn't
control that was really controlling them
and that they could bargain with it in
the way you could bargain with the
future you know in the way you bargain
with God you know and that you and and
at the same time the world like God he's
unknowable so I wish he talked a lot
more about what the hell he means by God
you know I heard him talking to Matt
Dillahunty about sort of God and taking
LSD in there no mate you know you're on
the wrong track here you know I don't
what just just tell them what you think
God it you know it's not it's not
mystical you know it's actually and I
don't know really where he stands as
I don't know how much of a Christian is
but I think that really appeals to me
that idea you know that the word God is
is is not what we take it to mean and
this is how the meaning of the word
developed as a powerful and often
malevolent force that we have to deal
with you know and I think that's um
that's a good definition of God this is
a great place to end yes
thanks very much David I really enjoyed
that thank ya